<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Continuation of our weekly newes containing these particulers following, the warlike proceedins and good successe of the French and their confederates in the Grisons and Valtoline, the great victories which the Hollanders haue gotten in Perue ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S460</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22454390</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22454390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25545</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25545)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Continuation of our weekly newes containing these particulers following, the warlike proceedins and good successe of the French and their confederates in the Grisons and Valtoline, the great victories which the Hollanders haue gotten in Perue ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.A. for Nath. Butter and Nicho. Bourn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Nouem. 22. Numb. 42.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 6 misnumbered 9.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. torn and stained.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 25201.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25545:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25545:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nouem. 22. Numb.</hi> 42.</p>
            <p>The continuation of our weekly Newes, Containing theſe particulers following.</p>
            <p>¶ The warlike proceedins and good ſucceſſe of the French and their Confederates in the <hi>Griſons</hi> and <hi>Valtoline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Victories which the Hollanders haue gotten in <hi>Perue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The taking of ſeuerall Townes in the land of <hi>Marke</hi> by the Forces of the Marquis of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the States of the vnited Prouinces.</p>
            <p>¶ The Incurſion of the <hi>Tartars</hi> vpon <hi>Podolia,</hi> when the <hi>Turkes</hi> inuaded <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ The Commaund of the Emperor to bring in all the proteſtant Bookes in <hi>Anſtria,</hi> and a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of all the Proteſtant Preachers to appeere at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna</hi> whether priuate in Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes, or others.</p>
            <p>¶ Certaine Letters from <hi>Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in</hi> concerning the meeting of ſeuerall Embaſſadors of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> with their conſultations with the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> concerning the recouery of the <hi>Valtoline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Death of the Lord of <hi>Southampton</hi> and his Sonne the Lord <hi>Wriotheouſly,</hi> with the valiant exploit of thes Lord of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex</hi> vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mies Conuoy, whereupon the Lord of <hi>Oxford</hi> receaued ſome hurt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ined of the Enemy ſome 20. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gons beſides o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther ſpoiles.</p>
            <p>With the Newes of diuers other Parts of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London Printed by</hi> E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for</hi> Nath Butter <hi>and</hi> Nicho. Bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25545:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25545:2"/>
            <head>The continuation of our weekely Newes, from <hi>Italy, Germany, Spaine, France,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and diuers other places.</head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna the 29. of October.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue receaued tydings from Caſhaw, that many thouſands of Tartarians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue made of late an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roade in Podolia, and haue done great hurt both with the fire and ſword, and taken many Chriſtians priſoners, euen about the ſame time when the Turkes did the like about the Townes which lye on the hilles and mountaines of Hungary.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25545:3"/>
               <p>His Imperiall Maieſtie is yet here, and the Stationers which dwell in Auſtria hauing beene commanded to ſend all their Proteſtant bookes into Germany, haue pack't them vp to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thitherwards.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtant States of Auſtria are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to meete here on the next day.</p>
               <p>All the Proteſtant Preachers and States of the Land of Ouer-ens are cited to appeare here and to anſwere for themſelues within the ſpace of ſixe weekes and three dayes; for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretendeth that they haue loſt their liues, lands and goods, by reaſon of their former rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and hath therefore commanded that none ſhall alter the poſſeſſion of their eſtates or of any part of them.</p>
               <p>There is likewiſe publiſhed by an open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that all the Proteſtant Preachers which liue yet with ſuch Lords in Auſtria, as haue beene faithfull to the Emperour muſt goe out of the Land.</p>
               <p>The States of the Land of Ouer-ens hauing gotten notice of this Proclamation, ſent the young Lord of Staremberg to his Imperiall Maieſtie (who maketh great account of him, to intercede and ſpeake for the Preachers that they might not be baniſhed.</p>
               <p>But being come to the Emperour to declare his Commiſſion, he charged him preſently to ſtay with it, vntill the Ambaſſadours of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25545:3"/> Land of Ouer-ens ſhould come to Vienna, and gaue him warning that although he ſhould bee ſent againe, he ſhould not ſpeake in the behalfe of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Breſlaw in Sileſia the 24. of October.</head>
               <p>The Coſſacks being many thouſands ſtrong, haue made an inroade in Sileſia, and pillaged amongſt other places the whole Countie of Pleſſe, ſo that the Princes, Lords, and States of Sileſia haue beene compelled to ſummon many of the Dukedome of Sileſia, to reſiſt them by mayne force of armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Prage the 26. of October.</head>
               <p>The Regiment of the Count <hi>Colaldo</hi> which lyeth ſome 14. leagues hence, is commanded to marche towards Alſatia.</p>
               <p>Fewe dayes agoe were the Proteſtant Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of this Cittie warned, that vnleſſe they payed fully (within the ſpace of fewe dayes) ſuch moneys as were demanded for their pardon, that they ſhould be baniſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25545:4"/>
               <head>From Prage the 29. of October.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Land-graue</hi> of Lichtenſtain maketh great preparation againſt his iourney towards Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na: And the Count of Waldtſteyn prepareth all manner of neceſſaries to bring an Armie in the field.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Cullen the 1. Nouember.</head>
               <p>The Spaniſh leauy yet many Souldiers, and them which they haue taken vp in the County of Rauensberg, they inquarter there at the charge of the Country people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Arnhem the 4. Nouember.</head>
               <p>It is here ſtill rumored that there ſhall bee leauyed for Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> and the Duke <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of Brunſwicke 20000. foote, and 4000. horſe. And the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the States of theſe vnited Prouinces haue choſen ſome Officers out of their Companies, and Cornets to leauy them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:25545:4"/>
               <head>From Antwerp the 5. of Noue.</head>
               <p>Wee vnderſtand by Letters written from <hi>Madrill</hi> the 6. day of October, how that the Duke of <hi>Oſsina</hi> dyed on the 20. day of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber laſt paſt, hauing beene ſome three yeares in Priſon, and that he was very repentant, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed his Baſtard Sonne (who leadeth the Neapolitan Regiment in <hi>Auſtria</hi>) that he would not acknowledge any Princes for his ſoueraigne but the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> or the Emperour.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Letters we learne likewiſe, how that the Fleet which is to Sayle towards <hi>Braſiel,</hi> to take the Bay <hi>Todos Los Sanctos</hi> again, was not likely to be ſoone ready; and that they hoped there that the Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of <hi>Braſiel</hi> ſhal recouer it themſelues, before their Fleete commeth there.</p>
               <p>The Ambaſſadour of the King of Denmarke hauing diſpatched his affaires in the Court of the King of Spaine, he made himſelfe ready to goe homewards. And it is rumored that the King of Spaine had reſtored the Daniſh ſhippes which were arreſted in Spaine.</p>
               <p>The King of Spaine ſent lately many Horſe to ſeuerall Princes: Namely, 24, to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25545:5"/> 6. to the Elector of Saxony, and 6. to the Duke of Bauaria.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Bruſſel the of 2. Nouem.</head>
               <p>They write from Antwerpe, that ſome 3. daies agoe, the Ordinance played very fiercely about Preda, and that ſome ſouldiers of the vnited Brouinces haue fought very cruelly with one of the Spaniſh Conuoyes.</p>
               <p>Moreouer this ſame Letter relateth a ſtrange thing which happened there, if we will belieue the Author, his words are theſe.</p>
               <p>On the 26. of October was heere one that went out of this Citie to make a triall to goe on the water, which he did afterwards, for hee went on a deepe pond being in his harniſh, &amp; armed with his rapier &amp; piſtol, in the preſence of many Lords of the Court &amp; Burgers of this Citty, and leaped and walked vpon the water as if it had beene land, and diſcharged there his Piſtol: Hee deſired entertainment, and offers to inſtruct ſome thouſands that they ſhall bee able to doe the like, and be fit to make any great enterprize.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25545:5"/>
               <head>Turin the 27 of October. 1624.</head>
               <p>SInce my laſt Letter to you, we haue beene at <hi>Suſa,</hi> where my Lord Ambaſſador went to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> and the French Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, and the Venetian Ambaſſador, to treat and negotiate with the great Conſtable of <hi>France</hi> concerning the preſent affaires in theſe parts, the Conſtable being accompanied with <hi>Monſ: le Mareſchall de Crequi,</hi> and with <hi>Monſeur de Bullion;</hi> the firſt being one of the greateſt men in all France, the laſt is priuy Councellor to the French King, being both annexed in commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Conſtable, and both in quality of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Ambaſſadors.</p>
               <p>The Marſhall <hi>de Crequi</hi> was likewiſe to condole with the D. of <hi>Sauoy</hi> in the King his Maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, the death of Prince <hi>Philipert.</hi> After their ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall at <hi>Suſa</hi> they had diuers meetings and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. Hauing beene ten dayes in the ſaid place they departed, we for <hi>Turin,</hi> the Conſtable for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25545:6"/> 
                  <hi>Grenoble.</hi> What hath beene treated, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Treaty is not knowne to any as yet, but the common coniecturation is, that they haue reſolued to recouer the <hi>Valtolina</hi> by force: and the Conſtable for the execution hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to make his Troupes paſse the <hi>Alpes</hi> with all poſſible ſpeede, notwithſtanding that Winter draweth neere.</p>
               <p>This is all I can ſay concerning the negotiation, time will ſhew vs the event of the buſineſſe: but one thing I feare much, the Ieſuiticall predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant power. <hi>Fiat voluntas Domini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the State of <hi>Milan</hi> they are all in armes, and in readineſse to oppoſe any that dare come.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of <hi>Genoa</hi> are more afeard then hurt, they take vp men <hi>alla Gagliarda</hi> to ſecure their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> haue ſent for Colonell <hi>Oben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraut,</hi> being ſtipendiated by them, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for all thoſe that draw pay of <hi>S. Marco,</hi> what their intention is I cannot tell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſeur de Tilly</hi> hath quartered his armie in the Marquiſate of <hi>Baden,</hi> and finding his forces too weake to keepe it, hath ſent for a ſupply.</p>
               <p>The <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>viſſes</hi> are all ſicke of a Lethargy, and wil hardly be put out of their drowſineſs, eſpecially being kept in this ſleepe by the Spaniſh piſtols, for the which by degrees they haue almoſt ſold their former liberty.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Archduke Leopold</hi> maketh a great ſhew of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25545:6"/> leauying troupes, <hi>ma non ha danari.</hi> God keepe him in that caſe. The Emperour hath ſent cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Commiſsaries to the Citie of <hi>Strasburg,</hi> with three propoſitions. Firſt, he deſires that the Magiſtrate of the ſaid citie ſhould deliuer all that are fled out of the Palatinate, with all their goods into his hands, and annexed to this is, that all that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath within that Citie (for they ſay hee hath a great quantitie of goods and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) ſhould likewiſe be deliuered vnto him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that they ſhould prepare a great ſumme of money for to pay the Emperours ſouldiers. Laſtly, they ſhould keepe victuals and munition in readineſſe, that whenſoeuer occaſion ſhould preſent it ſelfe that any troops of the Emperour ſhould paſſe that way, to furniſh them withall.</p>
               <p>The firſt propoſition they anſwered them, that in conſideration of the priuiledge and liberty of their City, they could not condeſcend vnto it: as for the other two, they anſwered, that in an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Diett they would reſolue as other States and Imperiall Cities ſhould doe.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Prage</hi> we heare that the plague reigneth there: and that the Proteſtants Church hath bin taken from them, and giuen to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> his Ieneſaries, (that is to ſay) his Ieſuits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:25545:7"/>
               <head>From Tarim the 9 of November.</head>
               <p>Very little Newes are ſtirring now being a dead time of the yeare, Winter comming on apace: being rather a fit time to conſult, then to effectuate any martiall Deſignes.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Milan</hi> wee haue certaine newes, that the Spaniſh miniſters haue intercepted a Packet of letters, ſent by <hi>Monſeur de Bethunes</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, reſident at <hi>Rome</hi> for the French King, to the Marquis of <hi>Corvare,</hi> likewiſe Ambaſſadour for the ſaid King, reſident in Suiſſerland: the contents of the Letter were theſe; He earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreateth the Ambaſſadour in Suiſſerland, to vſe all meanes poſſible to gaine the Suiſſes to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſome thouſands of men, the number not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exactly known by me, and thoſe to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the recouery of the <hi>Valtolina:</hi> whereupon the Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> Gouernor of Milan, hath cauſed ſundry copies to be made of the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſending them where hee thinketh they may moſt turne to the preiudice of the French, as to <hi>Rome</hi> to the Popes holineſſe, entreating him to conſider how little the French do reſpect his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, in reſpect that the Gariſons in the <hi>Valto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina</hi> were <hi>Milite di Santa Chieſa,</hi> and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt thoſe of the <hi>Valtolina,</hi> was as much as if he made war againſt the Church. Another
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25545:7"/> Copie he hath ſent vnto the Suiſſes in their Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta at Baden.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Berne</hi> wee heare that all our Proteſtant Cantons haue leauyed a competent number of men, for the defence of themſelues, ſo that if <hi>Tilly</hi> ſhould dare to make any incurſion, they may be able to withſtand him.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath ſent an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to <hi>Germany</hi> to aſſure thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States that the Troupes hee keepeth in the Empire, or is to ſend, is not with an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to vſurpe any imaginable thing, but that his onely intent and purpoſe is to ſettle a quiet and and ſtable peace in the Empire, and for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement and propagation of the Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25545:8"/>
            <head>NEWES FROM the Low-Countries.</head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Bergen op Zoom, Noucmb. 12.</head>
               <p>VVE receiued Letters from <hi>Bergen op Zoom</hi> bearing dare this twelfth of Nouember, 1624, that the handmaid of Warre, and ſcourge of great armies, a cruell Peſtilence, rageth and reigneth in his Excellencies armie in the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands: by the contagion whereof more haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed then by the enemies ſword or bullet. It doth not onely rage in the field, as at <hi>Roſendale</hi> and <hi>Longstraten,</hi> where the Prince of Oranges forces lye encamped, but the next good townes feele a portion of this calamity, as <hi>Breda, Bergen op Zoom,</hi> and others.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:25545:8"/>
               <p>The Prince of Orange, to the great griefe of euery good man, was grieuouſly ſicke of this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, but God be thanked, hee is reaſonable well recouered, to the vnſpeakable comfort of al thoſe who fight vnder his banners.</p>
               <p>The enemies did much reioyce at the report of this diſaſter: and it was giuen out in the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh quarters, that either he was dead, or elſe ſo deſperately ſicke, that hee was paſt all recouery. <hi>Quae volumus, facile credimus:</hi> It being an eaſie matter to beleeue thoſe things which our wils with affectation and earneſtneſſe doe deſire. But yet he liues, and long may liue to fight the battels of the Lord of Hoſts, and defend the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent from the ſword of the oppreſſor.</p>
               <p>But ſee how the Sunneſhine of this ioy is ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ouerſhadowed with a cloud of ſorrow for my Lord <hi>Wriotheſly,</hi> ſonne and heyre to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord my Lord of <hi>Southampton,</hi> who went ouer in this laſt expedition into the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, Captaine of a foot Company vnder his fathers command, being Coronell of one of the foure new Regiments, fell ſicke at <hi>Roſcndale</hi> in the Princes Leaguer; and to auoid the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of the field, he retired himſelfe to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen op Zoom,</hi> a towne not farre diſtant, there to vſe the beſt meanes he could for the recouery and re-eſtabliſhing of his health.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:25545:9"/>
               <p>But marke how Gods prouidence ouerſwayeth mens prouiſions and purpoſes. He had not lyen there many dayes vnder the tortures of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion, but he exchanged this mortall life into immortality, deceaſing vpon Sunday laſt was a ſennight, it being the ſeuenth of Nouember. His noble father comming to viſit his ſon to <hi>Bergen,</hi> fell ſicke of this Peſtilence alſo, and what with the violence of the ſickneſſe, and the griefe of mind for his ſonnes deceaſe, hee gaue vp his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and now glorified ghoſt into the hands of his Creator, the Wedneſday following, the tenth of Nouember.</p>
               <p>Theſe two, both the father and the ſonne, wee cannot too much condole nor mourne for their loſſes, they being as truly honorable in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as they were in their dignities and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
               <p>My old Lord in his younger yeares had tooke a taſte of the French and Netherland warres, and after that he was thought worthy by Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memory, to be Generall of her horſe in that expedition, which was made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> againſt the Earle of <hi>Tiroan,</hi> and other Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he caried himſelfe brauely and vnblemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He was a braue Souldier, both for his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and knowledge, and likewiſe learned, as hee was military and valiant.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:25545:9"/>
               <p>Beſides he was a great fauorer and <hi>Mecaenas</hi> vnto Armes and Artes, and a liberall acknowledger and rewarder of thoſe who could challenge any dignity from theſe profeſſions.</p>
               <p>His Sonne was the True Image and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of his Father, ſo that without wronging others by way of comparriſon, he was as hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as any young Noble-man in Chriſtendome whatſoeuer. But Is feare me that my poore Panegericke, and commendation doth rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace them: then dignifie their Worthyneſſe; wherefore I will fall from it and a little looke vpon Marquis <hi>Spinolaes:</hi> Leagur, where you ſhall ſee the ſickneſſe raine as bad, as in our Mauritian Quarters.</p>
               <p>The Famine griping the hungry maw of your poore ſouldier, the Itallians and Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards two Nations who can better indure the Schorching heat, then the cold of Winter, moſt vehement for the moſt partes in theſe Northerne Countries, curſing the ambition of their Prince, which muſt make their bodies fight againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable difficulties of nature; and therefore for theſe reſpects inclining to mutiny and hardly to be commanded.</p>
               <p>To aggriuate which calamities, the Marques his Souldiers runne away by parties euery day, their pay falls ſhort, and their Conuoyes which bring their Ammunition bread and other victualls, are dayly cut off by the States Souldiers comming from <hi>Roſendale, Long ſtraten</hi> and elſewhere. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt it is commonly reported, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25545:10"/> moſt certainely auerred by Letters written from <hi>Geertruydenbergh,</hi> and dated the ninth of this Moneth, that my Lord of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Oxford,</hi> going out vppon a party to ſeeke ſome aduenture, met with a Conuoy of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as they were trauailing from the further moſt parts of <hi>Brabante,</hi> vnto Marqueſſe <hi>Spinolaes</hi> quarter.</p>
               <p>Our Engliſh greedy of the pray and Honour beſides, giue in roundly vpon theſe Conuoyes, and after ſome reſiſtance make themſelues Maſters of the Waggon-men, and victualls.</p>
               <p>But yet it was not <hi>Incruento Victoria,</hi> for ſome men were loſt of both ſides, and my Lord of <hi>Oxford</hi> carryed away an Honorable Skarre, and the teſtimony of his vallor, being wounded in this conflict.</p>
               <p>There were twenty waggons or vpwards loſt by the Enemies with diuers ſpoyles of good vallew, which was truely and equally deuided amongſt the Souldiers who were Actors in this exployt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Newes from SPAINE.</head>
               <p>Wee receiued certaine information by letters dated at the <hi>Growine,</hi> about the middeſt of this laſt Month, that there is great preparation for a mighity Fleete in <hi>Gallicia, Biſca,</hi> and other the more Southerne parts of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are beſides the Sea-men and Marriners, ten thouſand Land Souldiers to bee embarkt in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25545:10"/> this action. And few of theſe are <hi>Behemies</hi> or freſh-water Souldiers, but ſuch as are of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of their old Garriſons. There is likewiſe a great impreſſe and ſtay of ſhipping of ſeuerall Countries, as Engliſh, Scots, French, and Eaſterlins to the great griefe and diſcontent of their poore maiſters and owners, who are like to ſuffer great detriment and loſſe by this meanes. The coniectures of this new preparation are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe: For ſome giue out that it is for ſcouring the Leuante and ſtrengthning of their Garriſons in <hi>Naples, Sicilia,</hi> and <hi>Lumbardy:</hi> Others thinke it is againſt the Grande Signior, and his Vice-royes of Tunes and Argiers, who make their Sanziake ſhips, and thoſe Harbours which are in them a receite of cuſtome for all Pirats. But thoſe whoſe iudgements are moſt curious: Iudge theſe prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be made againſt the Hollander for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering of <hi>Todos los Sanstos</hi> in <hi>Braſilia,</hi> which we may the ſooner be induſt to beleeue, if we ſhall but once conſider, how loath the Spaniards are to part with any thing which they haue once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated and made their owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Out of <hi>Swiſserland</hi> the 25. of <hi>October.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>His Maieſty of <hi>France</hi> leauieth yet dayly many men, and our Commiſſioners which haue beene ſent to his Maieſty are come backe againe with great ſatiſfaction, and haue reported that they diſpatched their affaires according to their owne minde, and that he hath promiſed to lend vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25545:11"/> his helping hand, and hath moreouer giuen charge to Monſieur <hi>Ladiguera</hi> to looke to vs and to leauy yet eight regiments of foote, and 2000 horſe to aſſiſt vs.</p>
               <p>They of <hi>Baſil</hi> being affrayd of a ſiedge, haue receiued yet 3000 men into their City, beſides great ſtore of powder and lead, and they are moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fetching dayly more prouiſion of victualls for them out of the Country there about: Monſieur <hi>de Chrich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as was mentioned before, is with 15000 foote, and 2000. horſe gone into <hi>Sauoy:</hi> And Monſieur <hi>de Convre</hi> who hath taken ſome paſſages of great importa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce in <hi>Veltolina,</hi> hath both there and in <hi>Swiſſerland,</hi> leauied many thouſands of Souldiers: And the three Sonnes of the Gouernor of <hi>Lyons</hi> haue likewiſe gotten Patents to leauy each a Regiment.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Souldiers which are leauied in the City of <hi>Bearne,</hi> and are many thouſandes ſtrong, haue had the firſt sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>miſh with them of the houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> which are in the <hi>Veltolina,</hi> and haue ſlaine many of them, and haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges about <hi>Chur,</hi> with a reſolution to beſiedge the ſame Towne: whereupon the Gouernour of <hi>chur</hi> hath written to the Arch-duke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> for ayde.</p>
               <p>They of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> doe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he meane time likewiſe what they can, and fortifie the Caſtles of <hi>Cleue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and of <hi>Della Riva,</hi> and prouide them with all manner of neceſſaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:25545:11"/>
               <head>From <hi>Lyons</hi> the 31 of this Moneth.</head>
               <p>The Secretary of Mounſier <hi>Ladiguiera</hi> is ſent to this Citty as a priſoner by his Maſter, becauſe he hath giuen intelligence to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee haue heere tidings that the Duke of <hi>Boulion</hi> is gone with great ſtore of mony to Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiur <hi>Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guiera,</hi> by order of our King of <hi>France:</hi> who hath giuen him order to ſet with his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Army vpon <hi>Voltolina,</hi> if the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris</hi> or the <hi>Pope</hi> will not reſtore it preſently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Roſendale</hi> the 7 of Nouember.</head>
               <p>Few dayes agoe ſent the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny horſe abroad, without any Cornets vpon good intelligence which he had receiued, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned within a while: with many priſoners and rich bootyes of our Enemyes.</p>
               <p>The Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> is now expecting ſome prouiſion which is comming out of <hi>Arto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Henegow:</hi> with ſome 4000. waggons, and ſeeing that he hath vnderſtood that our Forces are wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon it, he hath giuen order that all the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes which it is to come, ſhall along be intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and that they ſhall haue 3000 horſe and 6000 foote to conuey them to his Camp.</p>
               <p>From hence are many fire-lookes carryed to the Camp of Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> and wee vnderſtand by good intelligence that although the Conuoy of the Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> was lately
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25545:12"/> twice vpon the way to come from <hi>Shertogenboſh</hi> to the Camp, that it returned neuertheleſſe euery time, ſeeing it was not ſtrong enough in reſpect of our Forces which waited vpon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Amſterdam</hi> the 9 of Nouemb.</head>
               <p>With the laſt Letters of <hi>Spaine</hi> we vnderſtand that they were there very confuſed, by reaſon of the confirmation of the laſt newes, namely how that the Generall <hi>L'Hermite</hi> hath not onely taken and Pillaged <hi>Lima, Arika,</hi> and <hi>Poidſi,</hi> but likewiſe many other ſtrong Holds, and Fortes, and was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortifying himſelfe vpon the Sea-coaſts of <hi>Peru,</hi> where was come ſuch a feare amongſt the Inhabitants, by reaſon of the great ayde which hee hath of the King of <hi>Chilly,</hi> that they forſooke in many Places both Houſes, and Lands.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Bremen,</hi> that the Drumme was there dayly ſounded, to leauey both Horſe and Foote, for the High and Mighty Lords, the States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces, and that the Count of <hi>Lippe</hi> was likewiſe gone into the Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> to leauie there a Regiment of Foote for Count <hi>Mansfield.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer we vnderſtand by ſeuerall Letters, written out of the Dukedome of <hi>Gelderland</hi> how that ſome ſouldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Marquis of <hi>Brandenborg,</hi> and of the Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Vnited Prouinces haue lately taken d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs Townes in the County of <hi>Marke</hi> from the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25545:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
